Guide to the Crown Heights History Project collection 1994.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Crown Heights History Project oral histories, 1993 to 1994; 1993; 22321; 76.31 Gigabytes
  - De Shong, Roxanne, 1993 August 29; 1994.006.07; 22330
    In the interview, Wilder and De Shong discuss the cultural differences between Carribean and American born people, the stereotypes associated with West Indians and Jamaicans, and the changes in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn between when she arrived and at the time of the interview in 1993 citing the presence crime, violence, and drugs. The two also discussed the misperceptions, housing, and safety inequities between the Lubavitch and Black neighborhood residents, the struggle to live in Crown Heights, and her son's relationship to Gavin Cato. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Children -- Death; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Crown Street (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Rastafarians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Saint Vincent and the Grenadines; Cato, Gavin; Clara Barton High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); De Shong, Roxanne; Holy Spirit Catholic School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Rosenbaum, Yankel
  - Goldman, Esther, 1993 August 16; 1994.006.08; 22331
    Esther Goldman was born in Poland in 1926. An observant Jew from birth, she came to New York with her mother and siblings in 1934, joining her father who had arrived two years earlier. After living in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn for several years, Goldman's family moved to Eastern Parkway in the Crown Heights neighborhood in 1941. After marrying and briefly living in Philadelphia, Goldman returned to Crown Heights with her husband, and they had four children together. With Goldman's children grown and out of the house, she began working for a company on Broadway and Spring Street in Manhattan.
    Esther Goldman discusses her upbringing in Poland, East New York and on Eastern Parkway in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She recalls the growing Lubavitch movement of the mid to late twentieth century, and traces her own life's journey through the milieu of faith, family, neighbors, white flight, and historic events – ending in the 1991 Crown Heights riot and its aftermath. Interview conducted by Aviva Segall.
    Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z United States; Mass media and ethnic relations; Multiculturalism; Philadelphia (Pa.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Goldman, Esther; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; Sharpton, Al
  - Haynes, Joseph Harold, 1993 August 31; 1994.006.09; 22332
    Joseph Harold Haynes, African American, grew up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Crown Heights neighborhoods of Brooklyn. He attended Haaren High School for aviation studies and received a degree in mechanical engineering from the University of Missouri. Mr. Haynes was employed as a mechanical engineer for the New York City Transit Authority and as an accident investigator for the National Transportation Safety Board. He was a licensed commercial pilot and flight instructor. A contributor, to the now defunct, New Muse Community Museum, Joseph Haynes was a founding member of the Society for the Preservation of Weeksville. Haynes was in his 60s at the time of his interview. He died March 2, 1997.
    In the interview, Haynes discusses growing up in central Brooklyn during the 1940s and '50s; the importance of family, during this period; racial segregation; his passion for aviation; the Muse Community Museum; the founding of the Society for the Preservation of Weeksville; the 1991 riot in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and the future of race relations. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Weeksville (New York, N.Y.); Cato, Gavin; Haynes, Joseph Harold; New York City Transit Authority; Rosenbaum, Yankel; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History
  - Ince, Iyedun, 1993 August 15; 1994.006.10; 22333
    At the time of the interview in 1993, African American Ince Iyedun was twenty years old. Born in Harlem, New York, he and his brother Ojo Ashegun were raised by a single mother in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended parochial and public schools in the area; graduating from Brooklyn Technical High School. As of 2016, he is a djembe musician and teacher in New York City.
    The narrator discusses his childhood in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights, the disillusionment he experienced in high school and the decline of the youth culture of Crown Heights. He describes his own struggle to define himself and free himself from the pressures of his generation. He discusses possible approaches to changing the social environment of the neighborhood and concludes the interview with advice directed to the youth of Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blacks |x Race identity; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Technical High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Ince, Iyedun
  - Jacobson, Simon, 1993 August 19; 1994.006.11; 22335
    Rabbi Simon Jacobson was born in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights in 1956. Observant from birth, he attended Lubavitch Yeshiva and lived on St. Marks Avenue before moving to Sullivan Place. His father was Gershon Jacobson, founder and publisher of the Yiddish-language Hasidic newspaper Der Algemeiner. For several years Simon worked as the editor and translator of speeches by the Lubavitch Rebbe, Menachem Schneerson. Later, he became the director of Vaad Hanochos Hatmimim, a foundation that promotes Schneerson's teachings. A noted teacher in the community, he is the founder of a Lubavitch organization for outreach and education called the Meaningful Life Center, based on Eastern Parkway.
    Rabbi Simon Jacobson narrates his childhood in Crown Heights during the 1950s and '60s, recounting how the ethnic and religious composition of the Brooklyn neighborhood (including among different Hasidic movements) has changed throughout his lifetime. He explains the religious reasons for why the Lubavitch have stayed in Crown Heights (when other Jewish groups have left), and he addresses various subjects related to home-ownership—including role played by the Crown Heights Jewish Community Council and the perception that the Lubavitch want to drive Blacks out of the neighborhood. He describes the Lubavitch community's relationship with non-Jews and non-practicing Jews, dwelling on the concept of "chosenness." He and the interviewer discuss possible venues for outreach and cultural "translation"—especially of Jewish holidays and the concept of Moshiach (or messiah). Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Antisemitism; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish religious education; Jews |x Return to Orthodox Judaism; Judaism; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Race relations -- United States; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Jacobson, Simon; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
  - Kamman, Baila, 1993 October 17; 1994.006.12; 22336
    Baila Kamman was born in the Bronx, New York to middle class, secular Jewish parents. While on a summer vacation during her stint as a New York City public school teacher, she found herself in Israel during the 1973 Arab-Israeli War. The experience left Baila with a renewed interest in her religious heritage. Opting to relocate to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights along with a group of similarly worldly women seeking an Orthodox Jewish lifestyle, Baila and her friends faced a steep learning curve in trying to navigate the traditions and mores of their new lifestyle and neighborhood. She married and managed to complete a law degree while raising five children. After relocating to Rockland County, New York from the late 1980s to early '90s, Baila and her husband were residing in Crown Heights in 1993.
    Kamman, in her 40s, discusses her secular upbringing in a Bronx neighborhood filled with both Reform and Orthodox Jews, college in Queens, as well as her life as a young public elementary school teacher during the 1970s. She recounts the life-altering experience of finding herself in Israel during the 1973 Arab-Israeli War and the steps leading up to her eventual entree into the world of Lubavitch Hasidism, as well as how this new conservative lifestyle contradicted many of her 1960s-era values. Baila also details the offbeat courtship that led to her marriage, remembers escalating racial tensions leading up to the Crown Heights neighborhood riot of 1991 and explains how her father's death inspired her to attain a law degree while raising five children. Interview conducted by Aviva Segall.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Arab-Israeli conflict; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Feminism |z New York (State) |z New York; Israel; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Reformed Judaism; Rockland County (N.Y.); Saint Paul (Minn.); Abehsera, Michel; Cato, Gavin; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Kamman, Baila; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; Sharpton, Al
  - Kleinman, Zalman, 1993 July 21; 1994.006.13; 22337
    In 1933, Zalman Kleinman was born a Lubavitcher in Leningrad in the former Soviet Union. After the death of his parents, he and his sister were sent to Siberia, where he was adopted by a rabbi. For a time he lived in the Central Asian state of Sumerkand, amongst the Bukharian Jews. Kleinman immigrated to Paris, where he studied at an underground Lubavitch yeshiva. From Paris, he traveled to Israel where he began painting. He returned to Paris where he met and married his wife Rosa. In 1958, they immigrated to New York City and to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. An esteemed artist who painted Jewish life within the Hasidic community, Kleinman died in 1995.
    In the interview, the narrator discusses his childhood in Communist Russia; his adoption; life after World War II; immigrating to Paris, Israel and New York; meeting his wife; family life in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights; being an artist in a religious community and the making of a good family. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Artists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Children's literature; Israel; Jews, Russian |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z United States |y 20th century; Paris (France); Russia; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Uzbekistan; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Kleinman, Zalman
  - Kosher Cookbook Committee, 1993; 1994.006.14; 22338
    Esther Blau, 40s with twelve children, was born into a Lubavitch family in the midwest and moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn when she married. She gathered colleagues of the Cookbook Committee to discuss many aspects of life in Crown Heights.
    Kashruth, or the laws of keeping kosher, is one small part of this discussion.
    Access to this recording is restricted by the donor. Please contact library@brooklynhistory.org for further questions.
  - Lezama, Carlos, 1993 May 13; 1994.006.15; 22339
    Carlos Lezama was born in 1923 in Coro, Venezuela. He grew up in Trinidad but later returned to Venezuela, where was an auto-worker for General Motors and Chrysler, as well as a mechanic in Caracas specializing in dental machinery. After that, he departed for a job as a merchant mariner. It was during his travels as a seaman that he first visited the United States and eventually resolved to move to New York City, which he did—alone—in 1954. He had lived in Manhattan for about two years when he noticed the greater movement of Caribbean people into the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and followed suit. At some point, his wife and children joined him; they were all congregants at Saint Gregory Catholic Church. He continued to work as a mechanic, taking vocational courses to supplement his training, and after a while was able to buy a home on St. Johns Place. During this time, he became a prominent figure in the cultural life of Crown Heights' West Indian residents. Along with Rufus (Lionel) Gorin, he was a key organizer of the first Carnival parade on Labor Day that went down Eastern Parkway, now commonly called the West Indian Day Parade, in 1969. When Gorin died, Lezama was elected the first president of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA)—a position to which he was repeatedly reelected until he retired in 2002. Located on Eastern Parkway and now called the West Indian Day Parade, and remained president of the Carnival Association for nearly forty years. He died in 2007.
    Lezama spends the better part of his narration recounting the many years he has lived in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He describes his life in Venezuela as a young man, the experience of moving to New York on his own, and the steps he took toward settlement and—eventually—home-ownership. He relates the personal facts of his life to the observations he has made about Caribbean immigrants in general, and he favorably compares the openness of the present-day West Indian community to the more isolated, almost sectarian environment that he encountered when he first arrived in the 1950s. In particular, he describes an improvement in relations between West Indian immigrants and American-born Black people (an increasing number of whom, he notes, are from the southern United States). He tells the history of the Labor Day Carnival (or West Indian Day Parade), which he had been leading for twenty-six years. He notes that the parade has long been a source of tension and debate with the Hasidic Jews of Eastern Parkway; he ascribes the 1991 unrest that erupted around the deaths of Gavin Cato and Yankel Rosenbaum, in part, to this tension. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Caribbean Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic relations; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations -- United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Venezuela; Venezuelan Americans |z New York (State); West Indian Americans; Lezama, Carlos; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Lubavitch Child Rearing Discussion, 1994.006.16; 22340
  - Meshchaninov, Bracha, 1993 June 14; 1994.006.17; 22341
    Bracha Meshchaninov was born in Johannesburg, South Africa. At fourteen she began seeking a deeper connection to her Jewish faith and at eighteen traveled to Jerusalem, Israel to attend Neve Yerushalayim, an all-girls religious school. After graduating with degrees in English, guidance counseling and education from the University of Witwatersrand, she traveled Israel. At twenty-two, Bracha traveled to the United States where she studied with Lubavitch Hasidim. She soon dedicated herself to Yiddishkeit and married her husband Ilya. In her 30s at the time of the interview in 1993, she was a photographer living in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She now lives in Rockland County, New York, where she is an educator and Yoga teacher.
    In the interview, Bracha Meshchaninov discusses her childhood and family in Johannesburg, South Africa; her religious education in Israel; being a baal teshuvah (a Jew converted to Orthodoxy); her courtship and marriage to a Russian baal teshuvah; navigating a newly religious identity; the physical decline of the Rebbe and the spiritual ramifications within Lubavitch Hasidim and moving from the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Israel; Jews, South African; Jews |x Return to Orthodox Judaism; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations -- United States; South Africa; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Meshchaninov, Bracha; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
  - Meshchaninov, Moshe, 1993 August 18; 1994.006.18; 22342
    Moshe Meshchaninov was born in Leningrad, Russia in the former Soviet Union in 1954. Influenced by his younger brother, as a young engineer Moshe began exploring religious Judaism. This led to the family immigrating to the United States in the early 1980s. He discovered the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and the Lubavitch community in the late 1980s. A Jew who's returned to Orthodoxy, he met and married his wife Yehudis Chana, who's also a baal teshuvah. A resident of the Lubavitch community of Monsey, New York, he was a principal of a heating, ventilation and air conditioning corporation in 2015.
    In the interview, Meshchaninov discusses life as a Jew in Russia; his conversion to Orthodoxy; the family's immigration to the United States; and the Hasidic community. He suggests resolutions to the tensions in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Aviva Segall.
    Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Conversion |x Judaism; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews, Russian |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z United States |y 20th century; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Monsey (N.Y.); Persecution |z Soviet Union; Race relations -- United States; Russia; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Meshchaninov, Moshe
  - Milfort, Fritznel, 1993 August 17; 1994.006.19; 22343
    Fritznel Milfort grew up in Haiti. In 1972, he immigrated to the United States, where he was reunited with his mother and sister. He attended Thomas Jefferson High School in Brooklyn, New York. Mr. Milfort completed an undergraduate degree in accounting and a master's degreen at Long Island University. He is a licensed Certified Public Accountant, who has worked for the Internal Revenue Service, the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority, Mitchell/Titus and Oppenheimer, Appel and Dixon. At the time of the interview in 1993, Milfort ran a number of businesses in the Church Avenue area of the Brooklyn neighborhood of Flatbush. For most of his time in the United States, he's lived in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He continued to work in the field of taxation in a privately owned firm, as of 2015.
    In the interview Milfort discusses his immigration, and his accomplishments in education and the business. He also suggests ways in which the Haitian and African American communities can support each other. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    Accountants |z United States; African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Caribbean Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education, Higher -- New York (State) -- New York; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Haiti; Haitians |z New York (State) |z New York; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Taxation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Long Island University; Milfort, Fritznel; Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority
  - Morris, Evelyn, 1993 July 30; 1994.006.20; 22344
    Evelyn Morris, an African American, was born in Blackville, South Carolina, in 1935. At the age of eleven, she moved to New York City, with her sister, to reunite with her mother. She spent the remainder of her childhood in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. In 1972, she moved with her six children to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. At the date of the interview in 1993, Ms. Morris was working in a school cafeteria and still resided in the same apartment. A number of her children and grandchildren live within a close proximity. She was also employed as a food supervisor for the New York City Board of Education.
    Ms. Morris discusses the racial, religious and cultural tension of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. The core of the interview is a reflection on the cause of the racial tensions, between Blacks and Jews, in the neighborhood and her experience of the Crown Heights riot. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Migration, Internal |z United States; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations -- United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; South Carolina; Cato, Gavin; Morris, Evelyn; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Rosenbaum, Yankel
  - Neil, Clive, 1993 July 29; 1994.006.21; 22345
    Born in Mandeville, Jamaica in 1959, Dr. Clive E. Neil came to the United States on a soccer scholarship. He was an honors student at Eastern University and fellow at Princeton University. He has a master's degree in Divinity as well as a doctorate in Counseling from Drew University. He was ordained and served as minister at Tremont Presbyterian Church in the Bronx from 1985 to 1988. His pastorship at Bedford-Central began in 1988. He has written three books, taught and lectured at area colleges, enrolled as a Ministry Leadership Network scholar, and fathered two children.